<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>makefiles on Jiby&#39;s toolbox</title>
    <link>https://jiby.tech/tags/makefiles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in makefiles on Jiby&#39;s toolbox</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jiby.tech/tags/makefiles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Documenting Makefiles via a help message</title>
      <link>https://jiby.tech/post/make-help-documenting-makefile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jiby.tech/post/make-help-documenting-makefile/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve written in the past about using Makefiles for build automation and documentation. But sometimes I wish to provide help to users, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t require being a Makefiles expert to read!
Let&amp;rsquo;s explore how we can teach users our build system by turning the project&amp;rsquo;s Makefile (and awk) into a cheap documentation-as-code tool.
What it looks like make help Code Snippet 1: How to ask for help   Figure 1: Result of asking for help</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation: Makefiles for build automation and documentation</title>
      <link>https://jiby.tech/post/makefiles-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jiby.tech/post/makefiles-presentation/</guid>
      <description>Last Friday, I performed a presentation to my colleagues about Makefiles, and I want to share it to the public.
Of note, this presentation is setting aside what people usually know of Makefiles (autoconf-generated blobs, opaque to any inspection because machine-created), and instead I introduce the concept of file transformation as a graph, then teach Makefiles basics (using SQL commands as an example). We then move on to my plea for simple Makefiles, and their potential for both documentation (explain what your codebase commands are, to the juniors), and as lightweight automation (avoid typing long boring commands).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
