<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blog on Jiby&#39;s selfhosted effort</title>
    <link>https://jiby.tech/tags/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in blog on Jiby&#39;s selfhosted effort</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jiby.tech/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Git diff from empty commit</title>
      <link>https://jiby.tech/post/git-diff-empty-repo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jiby.tech/post/git-diff-empty-repo/</guid>
      <description>In order to troubleshoot a bug in the very early history of a project using git, I needed a way to show the git diff from &amp;ldquo;nothing&amp;rdquo; to the first commit. Since git keeps a linked graph of commits, what I wanted was a diff from the commit before the first one. Searching the onlines dug up this answer on StackOverflow, showing that there&amp;rsquo;s a specific commit hash we can use to diff from &amp;ldquo;nothing&amp;rdquo; to the first commit:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reverse-engineering webapp APIs with Firefox</title>
      <link>https://jiby.tech/post/reverse-engineer-api-with-firefox/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jiby.tech/post/reverse-engineer-api-with-firefox/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m writing code to back up my user data off a website that lets me see all of my info (including querying by time, account etc) but doesn&amp;rsquo;t have export features (officially). I am certain there&amp;rsquo;s an API behind the site that I just have to make sense of.
Since the webapp is requesting data from the API when I click, we should be able to record the web traffic to explore the API.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Git diff for prose</title>
      <link>https://jiby.tech/post/git-diff-lines-prose/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jiby.tech/post/git-diff-lines-prose/</guid>
      <description>When writing long sentences in documentation repositories, git tends to show really unhelpful diffs. They are unreadable because long lines aren&amp;rsquo;t broken, which hides edits happening towards end of line. A colleague of mine asked me if git couldn&amp;rsquo;t be configured to make this sort of thing more obvious. Challenge accepted!
  Figure 1: Can you spot the edit made in a long line of text?
  Kaushal Modi&amp;rsquo;s blog post on git diff for minified JS and CSS inspired this idea for all you prose lovers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Git pretty graph</title>
      <link>https://jiby.tech/post/git-graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jiby.tech/post/git-graph/</guid>
      <description>Get a cool graph of commits from the command line! For newbies and experts alike, git is a bit hard to visualize. Here&amp;rsquo;s a handy git command to make understanding git easier.
git log --decorate --oneline --graph   Figure 1: Git graph of this repository
  This can be made into a git command via an entry your ~/.gitconfig:
[alias] graph = log --decorate --oneline --graph Code Snippet 1: Alias &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presenting Android terminal with Termux (EdLug)</title>
      <link>https://jiby.tech/post/android-terminal-with-termux/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jiby.tech/post/android-terminal-with-termux/</guid>
      <description>Last night, I presented about Termux to EdLug, the Edinburgh Linux User group (see the event page on meetup.com) in a talk titled &amp;ldquo;The freedom of shelling out on Android&amp;rdquo;. It was tons of fun showing off how your Android phone/tablet getting a terminal unlocks a powerful tool!
  Termux running vim, gcc, strace, with tmux splitting screen. Credit: Termux website   I&amp;rsquo;ve made the slides available on this website, click on the slide below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First post</title>
      <link>https://jiby.tech/post/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jiby.tech/post/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my website!
This blog is meant to record some of the thoughts I keep coming back to, or discussions I&amp;rsquo;ve had over and over again with different people. My rule of thumb for inclusion here is &amp;ldquo;if you&amp;rsquo;ve had to say it more than twice, it&amp;rsquo;s time to write it down&amp;rdquo;.
See the About page for my background and motivations.
Look forward more posts as I try to condense my thoughts in written form.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>